The link in your bio on Instagram
is now dead.
Linktree is not being used like it used
to.
I did see something online about the
Reddit share prices falling,
but whether or
not I know that's true, I don't know.
All I know is that my behaviors on apps
have changed, and I think the behaviors of
a lot of people on apps have changed.
And I think the world of call to actions
as we know it has changed
and will not be the same forever.
A lot of people might think
that Linktree is on
its way out or losing its touch because
Instagram brought in its own
feature where you could pin multiple links
rather than just one link that was to
represent your brand, your business,
or whatever it was that you do.
But let's just look into some of the
components as to why this landscape is
changing so much. First of all,
it's never really going to be a social
media
platform's priority to have links to take
you away from platform.
All platforms are fighting their hardest
to keep you on that platform.
Whenever you go on YouTube
or you go on Instagram, that platform
is trying its
hardest to give you the best curated
content for your wants and your
needs. The second it doesn't deliver that,
you get bored, you leave, you go to a
competitor platform.
The monetization of these platforms,
the way they make money,
is by you sitting and spending time there.
On YouTube, that's sitting through ads,
Twitter, Instagram.
Even every time you open TikTok,
you get served an ad.
It's part of their monetization.
They want the first app
that you feel compelled to
click on when you pull your phone out your
pocket to be theirs.
So algorithmically,
there have always been a tendency to not
want
people to leave platforms. This
is why a lot of us theorize
that putting too many
links in your stories can then cause your
stories to not be pushed as far, because
it doesn't make sense for Instagram to
show your stories to huge amounts of
people if you've just put a link there
that's sending them to your latest YouTube
video, or to your product,
or to your landing page,
or to your website, whatever it
is. But then the other thing
is it can't stop you completely from doing
that
because if you get no traffic to those
links, you will stop using
that platform to
send traffic.
There has to be a fine balance.
Think about it from the majority of
employment nine till fives.
You are getting paid the least amount of
money for the most amount of work
possible.
That's almost what social media platforms
are doing.
They're giving you the smallest amount of
reach possible where you'll still use the
platform. Even YouTube
are pretty sneaky in the sense
that the amount of ads you're
served in a video if you're not on
Premium, and if you're not on Premium,
don't you
think you're a bit old to still be sitting
through ads on YouTube?
But anyway,
that's another video altogether.
YouTube algorithmically understands how
many ads you will sit through, and it will
serve you that amount. So
if you're someone that's just a bit of a
beta male that
gets served ads and go, "Oh,
they're just trying to make their money."
You sit
through them,
you're going to get served loads of ads.
But if you're an alpha male
that gets an ad, skips it the second it's
skippable,
you've got impenetrable armor
when it comes to the advertising world.
You get served less ads. Anyway,
it's not in a platform's best interest to
give
you loads of options to leave the
platform.
Linktree came along and understood
that you're a versatile business
and brand, and
that one link just isn't enough.
We needed a link tree so that whether
or not you
wanted to find out about your offers,
your newsletter, more
information or campaigns, donate,
I'm running for
charity, whatever it is,
you needed multiple options.
However, a lot of brands
and businesses then succumbed to one of
the biggest flaws
that you can make,
having too many options.
Having too many options is a bad thing.
Let me explain.
I've been using the same aftershave for
about four or five years
because every time I go into the
environment to try
and find a new aftershave,
there are quite literally too many
options.
Even my favorite brand has got seven.
I go in there, I think about something.
"Can I help you, sir?" "No,
leave me alone." And before you know it,
every single
time I go into duty free looking for a new
fragrance to represent myself with,
there are just too many options.
I get overwhelmed, and I leave.
I've always imagined the perfect world
where there's just a shop somewhere
with loads of options, but you walk in
and there's a guy who just
knows fragrances, probably gay in my mind.
I just trust them more with fashion
and smells and things like that.
And he comes over, and he looks at you,
looks you up and down, and goes, "Sir,
these three are the scent for you.
If you don't think one of these is the
right scent,
no worries." By limiting my options,
I feel like he's doing me a
service. He's doing me a favor.
He's not letting me be overwhelmed with
all of the
fragrances. Fun fact for you,
they pick the smell last
when making aftershave and
perfume. So they design the bottle,
the name, the branding, the color of the
box, all of these things.
They think about the person who this
fragrance is for,
then they pick the smell to match that.
So for any of you on YouTube,
you should make the video after you've
made the
packaging. So you make the title,
you make the thumbnail, because
if you make the
smell,
then try and make the branding for it,
it's just not going to do as well.
So if you give people too many options,
they will experience paralysis.
They'll freak out, and they'll be like,
"I'm out of there." Some of the Linktrees
I
go to quite literally give me anxiety.
Eight options. Eight options is too much.
Not to mention, if we take a step back
and go into social media 101, let's look
at the strategy for a second.
We get all this brand awareness.
We get people to follow us.
We get people to like us, whatever it is.
Hopefully, they like us. We then want,
at some point,
to tell them to go somewhere
because we're not charities.
We do need to do business.
Some people do like to send people
straight to a pay page. "Hey, go here.
Buy my product." I'm not a big fan of
that.
Everyone knows I have a four-tier system
for making sales.
Brand awareness, engagement, social media,
squeeze page, take someone's contact
information, email marketing campaigns,
and then a landing page.
I've done a lot of videos on this.
So I just can't help but feel that
when we do
calls to actions, such as, "Hey, guys,
and if you click the link in my bio,
you can get yourself a Yeti water bottle
for whatever."
I just can't help but feel
that the response from people is,
"I don't work for you.
I'm not going to your bio
and clicking your link.
What,
you think that I'm your employee now,
and I'm just going to do anything that
you say?" There's pushback. People
are sick to death of being told to go to
the
links in bio. Not to mention,
if I'm scrolling on social media,
and I'm just
going through scrolling, scrolling,
scrolling, scrolling, scrolling.
"Click the link in my bio." No, brother.
I'm scrolling, brother.
And the one thing that I
was wrong about that's really
revolutionized the way that
I get people's attention as far as call to
actions is using chatbots.
We have ManyChat, which I use.
I've actually had ManyChat since 2016.
I believe they're a partner with Meta now,
so for Facebook and Instagram, very
powerful tool.
And I think the benefits of a chatbot
are you can tell people to
comment or to DM. Now, there
are different automations.
If someone comments,
you can send them a single message.
If someone DMs you,
you can send them several messages.
I'll get onto that in a second.
And I think the curiosity of people is,
oh, if I
actually do this,
am I going to get a response?
And what is that response going to be?
There's almost that part of
inquisitiveness that we need and
that we want.
Think about YouTube again. A title
and thumbnail on a video should really
make
people think of two things, how and why.
Because if they're left with how or why,
they need to click to find out the answer.
So when you say,
"Comment the word aftershave," they're
almost wanting to know what
the response is.
What am I going to get messaged?
What am I going to get back?
What are they going to tell me? What
is the call to action going to be?
The link in the bio
is almost very predictable.
I think the other benefits of a chatbot as
well is if someone does that and they
get the interaction from you, that link,
that message, that call to action,
that compelling reason to do whatever it
is, is now in their inbox.
The majority of people on Instagram
actually treat it like an inbox.
I don't know about you,
but I kind of open up my inbox,
and then I swipe across
just to see what messages I've got.
I think I check my Instagram DMs sometimes
before my WhatsApp.
We just want to see what's popping.
Now, to prove to you the power of this,
so since I've been recording here, if I
show you my phone,
you'll see there's a lot of messages here
that say Seen.
If I just click on the top one, that
is an automation that went through this
morning, and actually,
even the one before that.
Let's just take any of these.
These are different automations
That I've been running.
There's seven or eight there within the
last hour alone.
ManyChat is doing work for me.
That post is two days old, and people
are still
engaging with it.
I'm getting chatbot automations come
through from YouTube
webinars that I did months ago.
For any of you maybe watching this on your
laptop
or your computer,
if you want to see this in action,
I shouldn't actually put this
in the video, but I'll put it anyway.
If you DM me the word "offer," you get an
offer that I put out months ago, and that
offer is for half price of my course,
which we took offline.
Officially, the course is $2,000.
That offer,
we'll give it to people for $999,
and people are still claiming it.
I looked at our accounts the other day.
I was like,
"How are people still getting the $999?"
It's because they're watching
a video that I put out ages ago with a
prompt saying, "DM me the word 'offer' and
you'll get it." If you DM me the word
"content," you get a slightly different
response. And this
is where I would say things would get a
little bit clever.
Sending someone a message, they're like,
"Oh, it's an automated response." But if
you DM someone,
you can set up an automation with delays,
pictures, videos,
whatever it is. I
was playing around with this a few months
ago, and when someone
DM me, I made it wait five seconds,
and then it messaged them saying,
"Hold on,
mate." Then another three seconds,
and then it said, "Sorry about this."
And then I
sent a video, and I upload
that video to ManyChat,
but it sends it to everyone.
It's me getting in a booth at work,
closing the door and saying,
"Sorry about that.
Yeah, running a 12-week challenge.
It's going on.
I think you'll really like it.
Use the link below." People kind of know
or should know that's an automation, but
it just gives them that personal feel.
Rather than, "Oh,
go to the link in my bio
and buy it," it's like, "Hey, DM me.
Let's have an engagement.
Let's have a chat." And also from that,
you can see
people that have gone through the
automation, but if someone responds,
that message
stays there. Easy for me to read. So
if I go to my General tab, scroll
down a bit, these are all automations.
Some people do ask,
"Have you been hacked?" Here we go.
Here's one that says, "Cheers, mate.
I'll take a look after work." I'll just go
back saying, "Legend." And then they'll
go, "Do you know what?
I've been hit with an automation,
but then the guy actually
messaged me back." Is
that going to improve the chances of them
doing business with
me? Maybe.
So I now have flows for loads of different
campaigns that send people to
loads of different places.
If you put in "offer," you get
that discount that I
should not be putting on YouTube to my
business mentorship.
If you put "content," you then get a
sequence that promotes my content creation
course.
If you were to say the word "challenge" up
until a few months ago, you'd
get information about my challenge because
you and I might run different
businesses,
so therefore I've got different campaigns.
Having a link in a bio
when I have a fitness app with 8,000
customers,
a business mentorship with 7,000
customers, or even might be running
campaigns to promote my books
that used to be on there
that I've used for videos.
They're in my office.
And allowing this means
that we can send some people to landing
pages, which does
take them down the funnel a bit,
some people to squeeze pages where we can
get
their email address.
And one thing that's definitely working
that's only started
working in the last few months
is using carousel posts.
So if you use a carousel post, you
are putting loads of photos together.
And as I've spoken about before,
you can then tell a story because in
video, the
story is very much the same. Introduction,
hook, set up, payoff.
Using pictures and carousels,
you can take your time a bit more,
and people can
swipe.
And the best part of a carousel post
is you get two chances to see it.
You'll get shown the first image, and
if you scroll past that,
you get the second
image.
So it gives you two chances with a
carousel to get the engagement that you
want.
People can swipe through up to 20 now.
So any of you that don't know,
maybe about a month ago,
Instagram changed to 20
photos for a carousel post versus 10,
which just allows you to elongate
that story
process. Now,
if you put music on a carousel,
it will get shared
to Reels and Explore.
And my manager actually messaged me last
night.
He goes, "James,
why haven't you put music on it?" I said,
"Mate, I don't want my
carousel to go to Explore.
I actually only want it to engage with
people that are
in my followers." The reason being
is this story only really
resonates with people that follow me.
Someone that never follows me before just
probably doesn't care, so I've done this
on purpose.
Then the last slide of the carousel tells
them to DM or comment a
certain word.
I actually set up two automations,
the DM automation with a trickle
effect of different messages,
and a comments automation so that
if they comment,
they get a comment reply saying, "Hey,
I asked you to DM me," so that they can go
into the automation to the way I wanted
it.
My experience is that
if you send people to landing pages,
you send people to buy,
sometimes they're just not emotionally
there.
Remember the four-stage system
that we spoke about before?
If you're sending someone from email to a
landing page, they've been hit with you a
lot. They know you a lot better.
They're closer to the brand.
They read your emails.
They're warmer as a lead.
If we take them from
that brand awareness top shelf
and send them straight to a
landing page,
the conversions just aren't high.
And although some people will see your
prices, they'll see the product,
they'll get
to have that psychological impact of
knowing what it is exactly that you do,
and
they might go away and a week later go,
"I'm bloody buying that thing I saw on the
page a while ago," for a lot of people,
it's just shooting your load too soon.
And some of my carousel posts have got me
up to 4,000 people on
my email list, which
if 10% of those end up doing business with
me, that's
great.
So do think about how you can utilize
these chatbots to do the work for
you instead of a click link and bio.
Another bonus to this is
that every time someone does comment
or DM you from a
story, a post, or whatever,
it bolsters the engagement.
Whether or not Instagram have changed
that algorithmically because they've
clocked
onto it, I don't know. And
if you can create some kind of compelling,
this is the
part, compelling,
something of interest to people, they will
give you their email address.
It's not PDFs. It's not recipe books.
You've got to think bigger.
You've got to think more value.
If it took you two hours to put together,
it's not really worth an email address.
There needs to be some element of blood,
sweat, and tears.
One of mine,
which I'll put a link to in the
description so you can just copy it,
so you can just rip it off,
is I've created 30 emails over 30 days,
which took
me a while. Each one of these emails
is a well-thought-out, curated way to
revolutionize and build your business.
And if people can get those,
by the time they do get the call to the
landing page,
they've already been warmed up.
They've already been taken through the
sales system
a bit more.
When it comes to using these call to
actions, when it comes to using
these chatbots,
I do think use them sparingly,
one in five, one in
10 posts,
because then it gives us enough time to
accrue goodwill, get in people's
good books. "Oh my God,
this person's really helping me." Then a
call to action.
And the best part is,
if they don't want to DM
or they don't want to comment,
that's fine.
You've left it there as a call to action.
Some of them will just do it out of
curiosity.
Some people may not even think they want
your product, but then they get the DM,
the automation.
They end up just checking out the landing
page out of curiosity.
The success ratios I've had from this
are just so much better
when compared to link
trees or link in bios.
Some people try to then not say link in
bio because they
think the algorithm's listening to what
they're saying and, "Oh no, this person's
trying to get people off our platform.
Don't give them the engagement they need."
I'm not sure how the future of call to
actions look, but if you're someone
that uses Facebook and Instagram, this is
certainly a step in the right direction.
You can have some fun with it.
Some people will think you're manually
there doing all the work.
Some people won't.
In some of my automations,
I actually make it clear at the end
that it's an
automation, but I say, "Don't worry,
I'll teach you how to do these automations
if
you join my program." This wasn't planned,
scripted, or anything like
that.
This is just me rifting on the landscape
that I see call to
actions because it's such an integral part
of our business.
If we can't get people from that brand
and awareness part down
into our sales systems,
it's going to be very difficult to do
business, which is
why it's important.
I thought I'd make this video.
So if you want to check out those 30
emails, 30 days, I'll put a link in the
description. Also put a link for
if you just want to check out what I do to
help
personal brands. And
if you're not interested, tell you what,
ask me a question in
the comments.
I look forward to getting back to you.
Cheers.